Robert Mumford MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Robert Mumford MD Papers
1950 - 1984
The Robert Mumford MD Papers contain his publications and research notes, presentations, and professional activities with St. Luke’s Hospital, Roosevelt Hospital, the William Alanson White Institute, American Psychiatric Association, American Academy of Psychoanalysis, and American College of Psychoanalysts. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
1.67 linear feet (4 boxes)
Mumford, Robert S., 1918-2005
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1983.0001
Gift of Robert Mumford, 1983 and 1985.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Robert S. Mumford was born on July 23, 1918 in Seattle, Washington. He conducted his undergraduate studies at the University of California at Los Angeles and completed his M.D. at McGill University in Montreal in 1943. Mumford received his psychiatric training from the William Alanson White Institute. His special interests and subspecialties included adolescence, the individual, family and marital problems, psychotherapy and pharmacotherapy, and teaching.
Mumford served as the attending psychiatrist for inpatients and outpatients at Roosevelt Hospital in New York from 1949-1970. He was also a consultant in the Obstetrics and Gynecology service. From 1958-1970, he served as the associate attending psychiatrist at St. Luke’s Hospital. In addition, he served as a consultant with the Obstetrics and Gynecology Department at Weill Cornell Medical Center.
Among other organizations, Mumford was a member of the New York County District Branch of the American Psychiatric Association and a Fellow of the American Psychiatric Association, the American Academy of Psychoanalysis, the American College of Psychiatrists, and the American College of Psychoanalysts (for which he served as Secretary-General from 1978-1982). Dr. Mumford died on February 25, 2005.
Mumford, Robert S., 1918-2005; American Psychiatric Association; American College of Psychoanalysts; American Academy of Psychoanalysis; Roosevelt Hospital (New York, N.Y.); William Alanson White Institute; St. Luke's Hospital (New York, N.Y.); Psychoanalysis; Sullivan, Harry Stack, 1892-1949
The Robert Mumford MD Papers consist of Dr. Mumford’s curriculum vitae, notes for a few of his published articles, and discussions of some papers presented at APA meetings. Records relate to his work at Roosevelt Hospital in the OB/GYN department, including a grant application to train OB/GYN residents to identify and manage psychiatric problems at Roosevelt Hospital. Most of the records pertaining to St. Luke’s Hospital concern a mental health study in college preparatory schools. Material includes the proposal, minutes of meetings, and reports in various stages of preparation.
Half the Mumford papers consist of membership applications for successful applicants to the American College of Psychoanalysts, for which Mumford served as Secretary-General from 1978 to 1982. Some of the applications date back to 1974. The applications consist of curriculum vitae with photographic portraits, letters of recommendation, and letters welcoming the individual to the organization. These records are organized alphabetically.
The holdings pertaining to the William Alanson White Institute address problems associated with the unique position of the Institute. There are also several folders of material from the American Psychiatric Association and the New York County District Branch of the APA. The latter deals primarily with the controversy over certification of non-medical professionals and with the arrangements for a 1967 APA meeting held in New York. Of special interest are the records of the American Academy of Psychoanalysis. These pertain to the dispute regarding certification of non-medical analysts and include the records of a committee on accreditation and certification. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Curriculum vitae, Undated (Box 1)
  - “Traditional Psychiatry, Freud and H.S. Sullivan” by Mumford reprint, notes and outline of paper, reprint requests, and comments, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Mumford on H.S. Sullivan, lecture and discussion at New York School of Psychiatry, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Published articles written by Mumford, 1961 - 1984 (Box 1)
  - Unpublished paper, “The Dynamics of an Operation Oriented Neurotic Patient in a General Hospital Clinic Setting” and program for APA conference at which paper was presented, 1955 - 1956 (Box 1)
  - Research on mothers and babies, 1963 - 1965 (Box 1)
  - Mumford's discussion of paper presented at APA meeting, “A Community School Mental Health Program” by Sheldon K. Schiff and Sheppard G. Kellam, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Mumford’s discussion of paper presented at APA meeting, “The Prognosis of Postpartum Mental Illness” by James E. Wilson, Peter Barglow, and William Shipman, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt Hospital - OB/GYN correspondence, reports, grant proposal, and article, “An Interdisciplinary Study of Four Wives Who Had Induced Abortions”, 1963 - 1972 (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt Hospital psychiatric conferences with OB/GYN staff, 1968 - 1970 (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt Hospital National Institute on Mental Health grant application to train OB/GYN residents to identify and manage psychiatric problems at Roosevelt Hospital, 1968 - 1971 (Box 1)
  - Lecture at St. Luke’s Hospital on OB/GYN psychiatric problems, 1966 (Box 1)
  - St. Luke’s Hospital, a mental health study in college preparatory schools proposal, reports, minutes of meetings, 1963 - 1970 (Box 1)
  - St. Luke’s Hospital a mental health study in college preparatory schools proposal, reports, minutes of meetings, 1963 - 1970 (Box 1)
  - St. Luke’s Hospital Center “A Mental Health Study in College Preparatory Schools”, c. 1970 (Box 1)
  - St. Luke’s Hospital Center “A Mental Health Study in College Preparatory Schools”, c. 1970 (Box 1)
  - St. Luke’s Hospital Center “A Mental Health Study in College Preparatory Schools”, c. 1970 (Box 1)
  - William Alanson White Institute, 1956 - 1965 (Box 2)
  - American Psychiatric Association Committee on Relations with Allied Professions, 1967 (Box 2)
  - American Psychiatric Association, 1969 - 1979 (Box 2)
  - American Psychiatric Association New York County District Branch, lay therapy, 1950 - 1965 (Box 2)
  - APA New York County District Branch, public relations, 1959 - 1963 (Box 2)
  - APA Arrangements Committee, N.Y. State Divisional Meeting, 1967 (Box 2)
  - American Academy of Psychoanalysis, 1963 - 1979 (Box 2)
  - American Academy of Psychoanalysis controversy over certification of non-medical analysts, 1963 - 1980 (Box 2)
  - American Academy of Psychoanalysis controversy over certification of non-medical analysts, 1977 - 1982 (Box 2)
  - American Academy of Psychoanalysis controversy over certification of non-medical analysts, 1982 - 1983 (Box 2)
  - American Academy of Psychoanalysis and National Accreditation Association and Examining Board of Psychoanalysis, 1981 (Box 2)
  - American Academy of Psychoanalysis Shadow Committee on Accreditation and Certification, 1981 (Box 2)
  - American Academy of Psychoanalysis Shadow Committee on Accreditation and Certification, 1981 (Box 2)
  - American Academy of Psychoanalysis Shadow Committee on Accreditation and Certification, 1980 (Box 2)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications A, 1974 - 1979 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications B, 1979 - 1980 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications C, 1977 - 1980 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications D, 1974 - 1982 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications E, 1978 - 1981 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications F, 1975 - 1979 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications G, 1978 - 1980 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications H, 1979 - 1982 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications I-J, 1978 - 1979 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications K, 1974 - 1982 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications L, 1975 - 1979 (Box 3)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications M, 1975 - 1980 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications N-O, 1976 - 1982 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications P, 1975 - 1982 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications R, 1975 - 1980 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications S, 1977 - 1981 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications T, 1978 - 1981 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications V-Wi, 1978 - 1980 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications Wo-Wy, 1979 - 1980 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts membership applications miscellaneous, 1979 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts transcripts and other material on colloquia, 1961 - 1983 (Box 4)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts miscellaneous, 1969 - 1975 (Box 4)